Much of what you know as Christianity and Islam today has little to do with the faiths themselves
and more to do with the U.S. Central Intelligence Agency. Some of the greatest thinkers of the
20th century made references to the large-scale weaponization of religion by colonial powers
in post-colonial societies. For example, in his book, Neocolonialism, The Last Stage of Imperialism,
Kwame Nkrumah wrote about the riptide of religious sects that followed after independence
from colonial rule. Franz Fanon in his book, The Wretched of the Earth, described how religious
tensions were inflamed and encouraged by colonial forces in the emerging post-colonial environment.
But beyond these passing references to the external manipulation of religion in the Global South,
how was this massive weaponization of religion actually done? Here's where the CIA comes in.
Between the 1960s and the 1980s, the Global South became the site of a war of religious ideas.
Some of these ideas were created to maintain and perpetuate the existing capitalist, economic,
and political hegemony, while others emerged to counter the hegemony or to spark local
political change. Under the guise of countering communism, the CIA infiltrated Christian movements
all over the Global South with the mission of steering Christian doctrines away from so-called
liberation theology. Originating in the Catholic Church of Latin America, liberation theology was
a set of teachings that encouraged people to stand up to corrupt governments and take collective
actions to better their lives. Because it was rooted in Catholic social justice concerns and it
borrowed from Marxist social analysis to understand and respond to inequality, U.S. state forces labeled the
communist, which of course made it a threat to be snuffed out. Over the course of several years,
the CIA, by its own admission, pumped millions of dollars into funding pro-capitalist Christian
movements all over the Global South as part of its anti-communist Cold War effort. It succeeded in
replacing liberation theology with so-called prosperity gospel as the most popular face of
Christianity in the Global South. This new doctrine erased any need for collectivism, instead encouraging
people to see their Christian faith and salvation as individualistic issues to be measured using
specific individual outcomes, such as economic blessings. You could now measure the extent of
your divine approval using the metrics of capitalism. So out went, love thy brother as thyself, and in came,
sow a seed of $50 to reap a blessing of $5,000.
As a student, I would just give what I had left. I said, God, this guy can't pay me tuition anyhow,
so I might as well give it. And I would go in front of chapel, meet up offering time, we'd give it.
And friends, two days later, from nowhere, envelope repairs in my mailbox with twice as much as I need
for tuition with no name on it. It was the perfect capitalist ruse because it convinced people to stop
thinking of progress as a shared national or collective issue, but rather as an individual
responsibility, which meant they did not need to organize into pressure groups, political movements,
trade unions, student unions, or any other collectivist entities that could be considered
leftist or communist. And it succeeded wildly, turning many of the world's poorest people in Africa,
Latin America, Asia, and the Caribbean into rabid, money-obsessed capitalists without capital,
who had lost the ability to see economic deprivation and its consequences as a political
problem. In the decades since the 1980s, prosperity gospel has established itself across the global
south, primarily through megachurches, whose pastors were almost invariably trained, mentored,
or connected in some form to the evangelical movements in the southern United States.
But the US empire did not attack Christianity alone. Early on in the Cold War, with the rise of
figures such as Egypt's Gamal Abdel Nasser and Libya's Muammar Gaddafi, the US realized the
potential of weaponizing Islam to serve as a bulwark against Arab nationalism and Islam's own
egalitarian doctrine. It collaborated with Saudi Arabia to create organizations such as the Muslim
World League, which funded the global spread of Wahhabism, a niche sect of Islam that exploded into
popularity in the 1970s and swept across the Muslim world. This form of Islam preached individual virtue,
total submission to authority, which made it a useful political tool for US-aligned capitalist
monarchies in the Gulf region and a vector for spreading individualism across the Islamic world.
This form of Islam would later go on to be associated with Al-Qaeda, ISIS, and other violent
extremist groups. By its own admission, the CIA also covertly trained and funded the Afghan
Mujahideen, which later morphed into Al-Qaeda in the Soviet-Afghan War of the 1980s. Ultimately,
it supported and continues to support the very Islamist groups that have contributed toward building
an atmosphere of violence in the Middle East, using a strategy that journalist Matt Domanthal has
described as management of savagery. For the people of the global South, religion has long served as
a source of soccer in an uncertain and unstable world. While some continue to seek escape from
today's complex realities by giving their time and money to CIA-affiliated megachurches in search of
personal prosperity, or resorting to senseless violence at the instigation of CIA-funded religious
organizations, we should all be aware that, as far as the empire is concerned, nothing is sacred and
nothing is off limits. War, so the empire, is not a shooting event at a single point in time. It is a
permanent and ongoing state of affairs in which anything, anything at all, can and will be
weaponized, including the beliefs and practices we hold closest.